Guide to the Emma Goldman Papers, 1909-1941 and undated RL.11353
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Emma Goldman papers
1909-1941 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Goldman, Emma, 1869-1940
RL.11353
0.8 Linear Feet
Emma Goldman was an anarchist known for her political activism, writing, and speeches. She played a pivotal role in the development of anarchist political philosophy in North America and Europe in the first half of the 20th century. The Emma Goldman papers feature over 300 letters, primarily written by Emma Goldman, although other anarchists, activists, and thinkers are represented as authors, including Alexander Berkman, Eugene Debs, Harry Kelly, Alexander Shapiro, and the Socialist Party of New England. Many of the letter recipients are unnamed (as "Comrade"), but the majority of the letters were directed to Thomas H. Keell, an English compositor and editor for the anarchist periodical Freedom, in London. Letter topics most often center around requests made of Keell in support of various writing projects as well as speaking engagements and organizing work completed in Europe, the United States, and Canada, but also touch on visa constraints for Goldman and Berkman, the state of the anarchist movement in various countries, the lack of support for anarchist publications, as well as general position statements, especially in regard to Soviet Russia and the Spanish Civil War. There are also papers related to various prominent anarchists. These include typescript drafts of four articles and letters by anarchists; nine handwritten articles on anarchist themes written in Italian by Errico Malatesta; publications; press releases; ephemera, including tickets, brochures, solicitation letters, handbills and flyers; a contract and room layout for speaking engagements; Thomas H. Keell's list of works on anarchism; newspaper clippings; and six black-and-white photographs. The Emma Goldman papers are part of the Lisa Unger Baskin Collection.
Arrangement
Organized into the following series: Letters and papers.
Biographical / Historical
Emma Goldman was an anarchist known for her political activism, writing, and speeches. She played a pivotal role in the development of anarchist political philosophy in North America and Europe in the first half of the 20th century. Born in Kovno, Russian Empire (present-day Kaunas, Lithuania) to a Jewish family, Goldman emigrated to the United States in 1885. Attracted to anarchism after the Haymarket affair, Goldman became a writer and a renowned lecturer on anarchist philosophy, women's rights, and social issues, attracting crowds of thousands. She and anarchist writer Alexander Berkman, her lover and lifelong friend, planned to assassinate industrialist and financier Henry Clay Frick as an act of propaganda of the deed. Frick survived the attempt on his life in 1892 and Berkman was sentenced to 22 years in prison. Goldman was imprisoned several times in the years that followed, for "inciting to riot" and illegally distributing information about birth control. In 1906, Goldman founded the anarchist journal Mother Earth. In 1917, Goldman and Berkman were sentenced to two years in jail for conspiring to "induce persons not to register" for the newly instated draft. After their release from prison, they were arrested—along with hundreds of others—and deported to Russia. Initially supportive of that country's October Revolution which brought the Bolsheviks to power, Goldman reversed her opinion in the wake of the Kronstadt rebellion and denounced the Soviet Union for its violent repression of independent voices. In 1923, she published a book about her experiences, My Disillusionment in Russia. While living in England, Canada, and France, she wrote an autobiography called Living My Life. After the outbreak of the Spanish Civil War, she traveled to Spain to support the anarchist revolution there. She died in Toronto on May 14, 1940, aged 70.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Emma Goldman Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2015.
Collection Overview
The Emma Goldman papers feature over 300 letters, primarily written by Emma Goldman, although other anarchists, activists, and thinkers are represented as authors, including Alexander Berkman, Eugene Debs, Harry Kelly, Alexander Shapiro, and the Socialist Party of New England. Many of the letter recipients are unnamed (as "Comrade"), but the majority of the letters were directed to Thomas H. Keell, an English compositor and editor for the anarchist periodical Freedom, in London. Letter topics most often center around requests made of Keell in support of various writing projects as well as speaking engagements and organizing work completed in Europe, the United States, and Canada, but also touch on visa constraints for Goldman and Berkman, the state of the anarchist movement in various countries, the lack of support for anarchist publications, as well as general position statements, especially in regard to Soviet Russia and the Spanish Civil War. There are also papers related to various prominent anarchists. These include typescript drafts of four articles and letters by anarchists; nine handwritten articles on anarchist themes written in Italian by Errico Malatesta; publications; press releases; ephemera, including tickets, brochures, solicitation letters, handbills and flyers; a contract and room layout for speaking engagements; Thomas H. Keell's list of works on anarchism; newspaper clippings; and six black-and-white photographs.
Anarchists; Anarchism; Press, Anarchist; Soviet Union -- Politics and government -- 1917-1936; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939; Press releases; Printed ephemera; Black-and-white photographs; Goldman, Emma, 1869-1940; Keell, Thomas H.; Berkman, Alexander, 1870-1936; Debs, Eugene V. (Eugene Victor), 1855-1926; Kelly, Harry, 1871-1953; Malatesta, Errico, 1853-1932; Baskin, Lisa Unger; Lisa Unger Baskin Collection (David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library); Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture; Keell, Thomas H.; Berkman, Alexander, 1870-1936; Debs, Eugene V. (Eugene Victor), 1855-1926; Kelly, Harry, 1871-1953; Malatesta, Errico, 1853-1932
- Letters, 1909-1941 and undated; 1
  Scope and Contents
  The Letters Series features over 300 letters, primarily written by Emma Goldman, although other anarchists, activists, and thinkers are represented as authors, including Alexander Berkman, Eugene Debs, Harry Kelly, Alexander Shapiro, and the Socialist Party of New England. Many of the letter recipients are unnamed (as "Comrade"), but the majority of the letters were directed to Thomas H. Keell, an English compositor and editor for the anarchist periodical Freedom, in London. Letter topics most often center around requests made of Keell in support of various writing projects as well as speaking engagements and organizing work completed in Europe, the United States, and Canada, but also touch on visa constraints for Goldman and Berkman, the state of the anarchist movement in various countries, the lack of support for anarchist publications, as well as general position statements, especially in regard to Soviet Russia and the Spanish Revolution.
  - Alexander Berkman (New York) to Thomas H. Keell (London), 1914 February 17; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 28 cm (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Berkman sends money and requests pamphlets. He also regrets Keell's news regarding the Labor Movement in England, pointing out that it wasn't the impression in the United States that the dock strike of 1912 and the miners strike were successful.
    Labor movement -- England -- History; Berkman, Alexander, 1870-1936; Keell, Thomas H.
  - Alexander Berkman (Stockholm, Sweden) to Thomas H. Keell (n.p.), 1922 January 12; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 24 cm (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Berkman provides instructions for printing an appeal. He notes his plan to write for FREEDOM.
    Anarchism -- Periodicals; Freedom (London, England: 1886); Berkman, Alexander, 1870-1936; Keell, Thomas H.
  - Alexander Berkman (Stockholm, Sweden) to Thomas H. Keell (n.p.), 1922 February 1; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 23 cm (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Berkman encloses an article for FREEDOM
  - [Alexander Berkman] (Stockholm, Sweden) to Comrade R. R. [Rudolf Rocker], 1922 February 11; 2 Leaves; 2 pages; 36 cm (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Berkman attempts to locate his missing diary, hoping that it is in Rocker's possession. He also writes his opinion of the New York World and the reasons he is moving forward to publish anarchist ideas in pamphlet form, rather than use the capitalist press. He would like Rocker's opinion on the matter.
    New York world (New York, N.Y.: 1881: Daily); Anarchism -- Periodicals; Berkman, Alexander, 1870-1936; Rocker, Rudolf, 1873-1958
  - Alexander Berkman (Stockholm, Sweden) to Thomas H. Keell (n.p.), 1922 February 15; 1 Leaves; 2 pages; 23 cm (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Berkman sends replies to items written in other publications. He requests that Keell call him "Alexander Berkman" so that he will not be confused with the Russian Communist writer, A. Berkman.
    Anarchism -- Periodicals; Berkman, Alexander, 1870-1936; Keell, Thomas H.
  - Alexander Berkman (Stockholm, Sweden) to {Thomas H.] K[eell] (n.p.), 1922 February 27; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 22 cm (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Berkman outlines instructions for printing several items in FREEDOM, and expresses his support for that publication's becoming a weekly.
  - Alexander Berkman (Stockholm, Sweden) to Thomas H. Keell (n.p.), [1922] March 2; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 11 cm (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Berkman encloses an article for immediate publication; reminds Keell to use his full name in publication.
  - Alexander Berkman (Stockholm, Sweden) to Thomas H. Keell (n.p.), 1922 March 14; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 17 cm (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Berkman recaps his recent letters, then reports on his travel plans, since he will soon be forced by the authorities to leave Stockholm.
    Deportation -- Sweden -- History -- 20th century; Berkman, Alexander, 1870-1936; Keell, Thomas H.
  - Alexander Berkman (Stockholm, Sweden) to [Thomas H.] Keell (n.p.), [1922] March 29; 2 Leaves; 2 pages; 35 cm (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Berkman describes his trouble getting travel visas in Europe, then outlines changes in Russian unions.
    Anarchists; Labor unions -- Soviet Union; Berkman, Alexander, 1870-1936; Keell, Thomas H.
  - Alexander Berkman (Berlin, Germany) to [Thomas H.] Keell (n.p.), [1922] May 9; 2 Leaves; 2 pages; 22 cm (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Berkman requests clippings of all his articles, and provides instructions for mailing them to his Berlin address.
  - Alexander Berkman (Berlin, Germany) to Thos.[Thomas H. Keell] (n.p.), 1922 May 16; 3 Leaves; 3 pages; 27 cm (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Berkman provides instructions for sending money via traveller's cheques, then comments on the development of a pamphlet. In a postscript, he outlines the reasons why any letters from members of the "Karelin group" in Russia, who are not recognized as comrades, may be ignored.
    Anarchists -- Soviet Union; Berkman, Alexander, 1870-1936; Keell, Thomas H.
  - Alexander Berkman (Berlin, Germany) to Comrades Keell [Thomas H. Keell] and [William C.] Owen (n.p.), 1922 May 25; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 29 cm (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Berkman seeks signatures for a manifesto regarding "Bolshevik persecution of the Anarchist, anarcho-syndicalist and other left-wing elements in Russia."
    Political persecution -- Soviet Union -- History; Soviet Union -- Politics and government -- 1917-1936; Berkman, Alexander, 1870-1936; Keell, Thomas H.; Owen, William C.
  - Alexander Berkman (Berlin, Germany) to Thomas H. Keell (n.p.), 1922 June 8; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 28 cm (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Berkman writes that he has finished the first of a series of pamphlets on the Russian Revolution, asking if Keell will serve as a distributor. Signed "S."
    Press, Anarchist -- Great Britain; Berkman, Alexander, 1870-1936; Keell, Thomas H.
  - Alexander Berkman (n.p.) to "K" [Thomas H. Keell] (n.p.), 1922 June 14; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 28 cm (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Berkman makes arrangements to send Keell the requested copies of his completed pamphlet.
  - Alexander Berkman (Berlin, Germany) to "THK" [Thomas H. Keell] (n.p.), 1922 June 29; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 29 cm (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Berkman notes that he has mailed the copies of his pamphlet and has received a new typewriter. He arranges for a friend to make a special contribution to Keell for publishing her articles, and discusses the possible price of the pamphlet.
  - Alexander Berkman (Berlin, Germany) to [Thomas H.] Keell (n.p.), [1922] July 13; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 33 cm (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Berkman expresses appreciation that Keell likes his pamphlet, but writes of his concern that Keell's publication does not receive enough material support, and hopes he will not have to suspend publication. Requests that Keell give timely publicity to the Manifesto.
  - Alexander Berkman (n.p.) to [Thomas H.] Keell (n.p.), 1922 August 26; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 28 cm (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Berkman requests copies of his book and pamphlet, then announces that he has the second pamphlet in the series ready for publication. Signed "S."
  - Alexander Berkman (Berlin, Germany) to T[homas] H. [Keell] (n.p.), 1922 Sept. 6; 1 Leaves; 2 pages; 29 cm (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Berkman notes that the second pamphlet will soon ship to Keell, then discusses advertising for it in FREEDOM. He writes regarding of an article that "contains only the old worn out arguments of the stand-pat bolsheviki." He then comments on the material support for FREEDOM that has come from Japan. Signed "S." The letter is accompanied by a receipt for Keell's contribution to the fund for Anarchists imprisoned by Bolsheviks.
    Press, Anarchist -- Great Britain; Freedom (London, England: 1886); Berkman, Alexander, 1870-1936; Keell, Thomas H.
  - Alexander Berkman (n.p.) to [Thomas H.] Keell (n.p.), 1922 November 18; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 29 cm (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Berkman requests that Keell send any funds he has on hand that can be sent to Russia.
    Berkman, Alexander, 1870-1936; Keell, Thomas H.
  - Alexander Berkman (n.p.) to [Thomas H.] Keell (n.p.), 1922 November 30; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 29 cm (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Berkman writes that he has completed the third pamphlet in his series on the Russian Revolution and asks Keell how many copies to send. He also inquires how the other pamphlets are selling.
  - Alexander Berkman (n.p.) to [Thomas H.] Keell (n.p.), 1922 December 3; 2 Leaves; 2 pages; 29 cm (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Berkman writes that of a shortage of pamphlets in the United States and requests Keell to act as supplier. He imagines how his third pamphlet will be misrepresented in Russia, and acknowledges that another anarchist publication, Free Society, has gone under. Signed "S."
    Press, Anarchist -- Great Britain; Anarchism -- Periodicals; Berkman, Alexander, 1870-1936; Keell, Thomas H.
  - Alexander Berkman (Berlin, Germany) to [Thomas H.] Keell (n.p.), 1923 September 30; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 29 cm (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Berkman mentions a "terrible disaster" in Japan, and that the firm there still needs to pay for pamphlets he sent. He goes on to discuss exchange rates and the preference for pounds or dollars over valuta. He adds that he has not been well, and has been unable to work on his book. Signed "S."
    Foreign exchange rates; Berkman, Alexander, 1870-1936; Keell, Thomas H.
  - Alexander Berkman (Berlin, Germany) to [Thomas H.] Keell (n.p.), 1923 November 7; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 28 cm (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Berkman again discusses the poor exchange rates for payments made in pounds. Signed "S."
  - Alexander Berkman (n.p.) to [Thomas H.] Keell (n.p.), 1923 Decenber 26; 1 Leaves; 2 pages; 23 cm (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Berkman sends his financial report for 1923, with instructions for printing, particularly in regard to explaining funds for support of all Russian prisoners versus anarchist Russian prisoners.
    Political persecution -- Soviet Union -- History; Soviet Union -- Politics and government -- 1917-1936; Berkman, Alexander, 1870-1936; Keell, Thomas H.
  - Alexander Berkman (Berlin, Germany) to Th{omas H.] Keell (n.p.), 1924 July 25; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 30 cm (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Berkman reports that he has been unable to find a publisher for his "pscychologic" study of the Russian revolution. He then notes that Emma Goldman will soon be traveling to England; news which must be kept confidential. He requests that Keell publish a note that the Joint Committee has issued 4 picture postcards to be sold as a fundraiser for imprisoned revolutionaries in Russia.
    Political persecution -- Soviet Union -- History; Soviet Union -- Politics and government -- 1917-1936; Berkman, Alexander, 1870-1936; Keell, Thomas H.; Goldman, Emma, 1869-1940
  - Alexander Berkman (Berlin, Germany) to [Thomas H.] Keell (n.p.), 1924 August 5; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 30 cm (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Berkman writes regarding publishing a reply to Guy Aldred in FREEDOM.
  - Alexander Berkman (Berlin, Germany) to [Thomas H.] Keell (n.p.), 1924 November 20; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 29 cm (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Berkman requests publication of an enclosed note. In a postscript he writes that he hears regularly from Emma Goldman, and another friend has brought news from London.
  - Alexander Berkman (Berlin, Germany) to My dear old friend [Thomas H. Keell] (n.p.), 1924 December 5; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 29 cm (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Berkman describes how he will distribute Keell's donation for revolutionaries imprisoned in Russia. He mentions an earthquake in Japan and that he understands Emma Goldman will soon be holding meetings in England.
    Anarchists; Berkman, Alexander, 1870-1936; Keell, Thomas H.; Goldman, Emma, 1869-1940
  - Alexander Berkman (Berlin, Germany) to [Thomas H.] Keell (n.p.), 1925 August 26; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 28 cm (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Berkman writes that he has made inquiries regarding M. Acharya, who is fine. He outlines publications to be sent to Acharya. Berkman comments on general labor conditions in Europe. He notes that he hears regularly from Emma Goldman, who has become close to her contacts in Bristol, England.
    Labor movement -- Europe -- History -- 20th century; Berkman, Alexander, 1870-1936; Keell, Thomas H.; Goldman, Emma, 1869-1940
  - Alexander Berkman (Berlin, Germany) to [Thomas H.] Keell (n.p.), 1925 August 31; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 23 cm (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Berkman thanks Keell for payment on his books and asks him to mail a copy of the Bolshevik Myth to France, for France permits revolutionary mailings from England, but not Germany.
    Postal service -- France -- History -- 20th century; Berkman, Alexander, 1870-1936; Keell, Thomas H.
  - Alexander Berkman (Berlin, Germany) to T.H.K. [Thomas H. Keell] (n.p.), 1925? December 9; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 29 cm (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Berkman provides Keell with his new address.
  - Alexander Berkman (New York?) to [Thomas H.] Keell (n.p.), 1927? May 8; 2 Leaves; 4 pages; 28 cm (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Berkman comments off the record regarding the lack of support from the I.W.W. for unemployment and anti-militarist movements.
    Industrial Workers of the World -- History -- 20th century; Berkman, Alexander, 1870-1936; Keell, Thomas H.
  - Alexander Berkman (St. Cloud, France) to [Thomas H.] Keell (n.p.), 1927 February 10; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 27 cm (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Berkman recounts his shock at Keell's plan to cease publication of FREEDOM, and wonders why their movement has not garnered broader support.
  - Alexander Berkman (St. Cloud, France) to [Thomas H.] Keell (n.p.), 1927 April 24; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 27 cm (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Berkman reports that he has been asked to write a book on anarchism by the Anarchist Federation of the U.S. and requests that Keell send him pamphlets and books he can use as reference works. He notes that all his books were seized in N. Y. during his arrest for deportation.
    Anarchism; Berkman, Alexander, 1870-1936; Keell, Thomas H.
  - Alexander Berkman (St. Cloud, France) to Thos. [Thomas] H. Keell (London, England), [1927] May 5; 1 Leaves; 2 pages; 9 cm (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Berkman writes a postcard to list the books he has recently received. He points out that Havel is also writing a book on anarchism. He welcomes Keell's help with material for his own book.
  - Alexander Berkman (n.p.) to [Thomas H.] Keell (n.p.), 1927 June 20; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 27 cm (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Berkman states that he will write an ABC of Communist Anarchism and outlines his plan for the book.
  - Alexander Berkman (St. Cloud, France) to [Thomas H.] Keell (n.p.), 1927 October 4; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 27 cm (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Berkman acknowledges receipt of funds on behalf of "imprisoned comrades in Russia." He then admits that he has done very little work on his book. He adds that Vanguard Press has issued a collection of Kropotkin's pamphlets, compiled by Roger Baldwin, of whom he doesn't have a high opinion. In a postscript, Berkman reports that Emma Goldman has not been well, and that he thinks the Canadian climate does not agree with her. He also requests Keell get him a three-month subscription to the Manchester Guardian.
    Anarchism; Berkman, Alexander, 1870-1936; Keell, Thomas H.; Goldman, Emma, 1869-1940
  - Alexander Berkman (St. Cloud, France) to Tom [Thomas H. Keell] (London, England), 1927 October 12; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 9 cm (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Berkman reports in a postcard that he is receiving the Manchester Guardian, but would like the weekly edition.
    Manchester guardian (Manchester, England: 1828); Berkman, Alexander, 1870-1936; Keell, Thomas H.
  - Alexander Berkman (St. Cloud, France) to Tom [Thomas H. Keell] (London, England), [1927] October 30; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 9 cm (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Berkman notes in a postcard that he is receiving the weekly edition of the Manchester Guardian, but finds it "as empty as a bottle of whiskey after a few Russians have been at it." He asks that the subscription be allowed to expire.
  - Alexander Berkman (St. Cloud, France) to K. [Thomas H. Keell] (London, England), 1927 November 10; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 9 cm (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Berkman thanks Keell for the New Leader, which he reads with greater interest than the Guardian. He requests the address for Roubchinsky. He adds that Emma Goldman has not been well in Toronto.
    New leader (New York, N.Y.: 1924); Berkman, Alexander, 1870-1936; Keell, Thomas H.; Goldman, Emma, 1869-1940
  - Alexander Berkman (n.p.) to [Thomas H.] Keell (n.p.), 1927 December 21; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 23 cm (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Berkman asks Keell to fulfill a request for a copy of his memoirs.
  - Alexander Berkman (St. Cloud, France) to [Thomas H.] Keell (n.p.), 1929 February 27; 1 Leaves; 2 pages; 27 cm (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Berkman writes that about his translation of the drama The Prisoner, and announces that his book is on the press. He regrets that Freedom is no longer being published. He then outlines his plan to collect First Flight covers.
    Anarchists. Air mail service; Berkman, Alexander, 1870-1936; Keell, Thomas H.
  - Alexander Berkman (St. Cloud, France) to [Thomas H.] Keell (n.p.), 1929 March 7; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 27 cm (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Berkman writes more about his plan to collect First Flight stamps and envelopes.
    Air mail service; Berkman, Alexander, 1870-1936; Keell, Thomas H.
  - Alexander Berkman (St. Cloud, France) to [Thomas H.] Keell (n.p.), 1929 March 20; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 27 cm (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Berkman writes to urgently request the special air mail envelopes for the flight from London to Karachi, India.